Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Cooperative Society Records 1936-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Cooperative Society Records 1936-1983
Ann Arbor Cooperative Society
As its name implies, the Ann Arbor Cooperative Society was a cooperative corporation that offered its members a wide range of services. These included a credit union, legal and tax preparation services, home insulation and maintenance services, memorial advising and planning services, vacation property, discount ticket sales to amusement parks, and bulk purchasing. The records of the Society reflect its diverse activities, and include minutes, financial statements, audits, manager's reports, by-laws, news sheet, correspondence, and subject files relating to cooperative projects.
85644 Bj 2
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The first accession of the record group was the gift of the gift of the Society (donor no. 676 ) and came through Susan E. Morrison in December 1988. The second accession was the gift of Helen Metzner (donor no. 9291 ), former president of the Society, in January 2003.
The record group is open for research.
The Ann Arbor Cooperative Society was founded in Ann Arbor, Michigan, in 1936 as a group of individuals banding together to purchase rock salt and coal. As the venture was successful it branched out to include other consumer areas such as groceries, gasoline and a credit union in the early years, expanding further to include an insulation company, insurance, legal, and tax services, trailer parks, recreational facilities and a memorial advisory and planning service as time passed. The purpose of the cooperative was to protect and advance the interests of its members as consumers and to provide quality items and services at reasonable prices.
The Society expanded throughout its first decade, growing from a bulk coal and salt buying club to include cooperative gas stations, grocery, and appliance store, testing and grading its products and educating members about cooperative ideals. However, the Society offered many of these services below cost, and could not keep operations running. The food and appliance stores disbanded around 1952, with the gas stations folding shortly thereafter.
During the 1960s and early 1970s, the Society started to recover financially, and began expanding its services again. Cooperative offerings included the Creduco insulation company, low-cost legal, tax, and insurance services, discount ticket sales, an optical service, and the Memorial Advisory and Planning Service. Around this time, it also became involved in real estate, buying a recreational camp site and trailer parks. Unfortunately, the Society's real estate ventures proved to be too much of a drain upon its resources, and it divested itself of land holdings during the mid-1970s.
Throughout the Society's history its affiliated credit union, the AACS Credit Union, was an ongoing and enduring success. By the mid-1970s it was largely independent, with its own holdings and Board. Over the course of the 1970s, its Board and the Society's Board grew increasingly antagonistic towards each other. Eventually, the Credit Union decided to split away and become the Huron River Area Credit Union, a move which was effected in 1981. The loss of the Credit Union was a serious blow to the Society, and despite ventures like a new food co-op, the cooperative was disbanded ca. 1984/85.
The records of the Ann Arbor Cooperative Society relate to its activities as a non-profit cooperative. While some material is extant documenting the early years, the majority of the record group is focused on the period from 1970-1983. Around a third of the available records are minutes to board meetings and financial statements, referring to the cooperative as a whole. The rest of the record group pertains to individual committees, projects, programs and activities.
This record group is excellent as a case study of a non-profit cooperative. The records provide information concerning the organization, its purpose, operation, finances and services. It is arranged in two series, Administrative Records and Board of Directors and Financial Records, with materials from the second accession incorporated into each of the series' files. While an attempt was made to place materials on specific activities and committees in separate topical -files, information concerning these can be found in the minutes of the board of directors, where all items concerning the cooperative society were discussed and reviewed.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Cooperative Society (Mich.); Consumer cooperatives--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Cooperative societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Administrative Records 1936-1983
  The first series, Administrative Records (1936-1983), contains topical files relating to a number of areas of the Society's operation, documenting the work of and on various committees and activities. It also includes articles of incorporation and bylaws, newsletters, correspondence, and records relating to real estate owned by the cooperative.
  - Ann Arbor Credit Union Housing Corporation Inc. (Box 1)
    (proposal, minutes)
  - Ann Arbor Insurance Center (Box 1)
    (minutes, financial statements, correspondence)
  - Annual Membership Meetings 1938, 1940-1982 (Box 1)
    (agendas, minutes, announcements)
  - Articles of Incorporation, Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Center for Consumer Education and Research (Box 1)
    (articles of incorporation, bylaws, agenda, IRS correspondence)
  - Consumer Information Cooperative (Box 1)
    (articles of incorporation, bylaws, minutes, certificate of dissolution)
  - Consumers Service Agency (Box 1)
    (minutes, reports, financial statements, history, memos, correspondence, stock purchase agreement)
  - Coop Auto Rally 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    (financial statements, correspondence)
  - Coop Credit Union 1957-1971 (Box 1)
    (minutes, financial statements, correspondence, flyers)
  - Coop Credit Union-Disputes with Coop Society 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    (correspondence, by law amendments, clippings)
  - Coop Store 1937-1940 (Box 1)
    (minutes, reports, financial statements, advertising, price lists, photograph)
  - Coop Store-Food Warehouse 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    (planning materials, minutes, reports, financial statements, correspondence, price lists)
  - Coop Store-Food Warehouse-How To Manuals (Box 1)
  - Coop Store-Food Warehouse-Recruitment Drive (Box 1)
  - Cooperative Auto Purchase Program (Box 1)
    (correspondence, memos, brochure, dealership lists)
  - Cooperative Services, Inc. (Box 1)
    (bylaws, objectives, printed materials, publications)
  - Correspondence 1936-1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1963-1983 (Box 1)
  - Creduco Insulation Company, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (articles of incorporation, bylaws, minutes, proposals, financial statements, correspondence)
  - Education Committee minutes 1951, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes 1972-1980 (Box 1)
  - General Information/Programs (Box 1)
  - Group Legal Service (Box 1)
    (minutes, financial statements, information, announcements, correspondence, membership lists)
  - Manager Evaluation (Box 1)
    (performance criteria, job descriptions, personnel reviews, resumes)
  - Membership mailings, flyers, publications (Box 1)
  - Memorial Advisory and Planning Service, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (reports, financial statements, correspondence)
  - National Consumer Cooperative Bank Proposal (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1936-1980 (Box 2)
  - Planning Committee Minutes, Reports (Box 2)
  - Recreational Facility Committee Minutes, Reports (Box 2)
  - Real Estate-Purchase, Sales, Mortgages (Box 2)
    (contracts, abstracts, correspondence)
  - Sesquicentennial (Minutes, Memos) (Box 2)
  - Students Credit Union (Box 2)
    (reports. proposals, financial statements, correspondence, advertisements)
  - Tamarack Family Camp (Box 2)
    (general information, purchase agreement, financial statements, correspondence, policies)
  - Tax Exemption correspondence--IRS 1977 (Box 2)
  - Tax Service (Box 2)
    (reports, proposals, budgets, advertising)
  - Ticket Sales Committee (Box 2)
    (reports, sales, correspondence)
  - (Straubs) Trailer Park Blueprint 1950 (Box 2)
  - Trailer Park Extension Blueprints 1961 (Box 2)
  - Trailer Park
    - Blueprints 1963-1964, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Closing Statement (Box 2)
  - Trist Road Closing Statement (Box 2)
  - University Cooperative 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (articles of incorporation, bylaws, minutes, financial statements, correspondence, printed material)
  - University Cooperative-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    (printed material, advertisements correspondence, photographs)
  - UCU [University Credit Union] Non-Profit Housing Corporation (Box 2)
    (bylaws, minutes, proposals)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    (calendar, survey, memorandum, strategies for obtaining goals, reports on members address search, etc.)
- Board of Directors and Financial Records 1936-1983
  The second series, Board of Directors and Financial Records (1936-1983), includes board of directors lists, minutes, operation reports, and correspondence. The financial records include income and expenditure sheets, balance sheets, budget projections, reports, and audits.
  - Board of Directors and Committee Lists (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Meetings
    (Agendas, Minutes, Reports, Proposals, Correspondence)
    - 1940-1970, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - 1971-1983, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Retreats 1975-1981 (Box 3)
    (agendas, meeting materials)
  - Financial Statements 1936-1983, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Audits (Incomplete) 1937-1940 (Box 3)